<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A counter-snarle for Ishmael Rabshacheh, a Cecropidan Lycaonite. By Sr. Edward Hoby, Knight, one of the gentlemen of his Maiesties Priuie-Chamber</title>
            <author>Hoby, Edward, Sir, 1560-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03413</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13539</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104126</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839865</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839865</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4324</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03413)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4324)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1352:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A counter-snarle for Ishmael Rabshacheh, a Cecropidan Lycaonite. By Sr. Edward Hoby, Knight, one of the gentlemen of his Maiesties Priuie-Chamber</title>
                  <author>Hoby, Edward, Sir, 1560-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 78, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Eld and Thomas Snodham] for Nath. Butter, by the authoritie of superiours,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Floyd, John.  The overthrow of the Protestants pulpit-Babels.</note>
                  <note>"Snodham pr[inted]. G-L; Eld the rest"--STC.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>In this state, [A]2v is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Floyd, John, 1572-1649. --  Overthrow of the Protestants pulpit-Babels --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4324:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4324:1"/>
            <p>A Counter-ſnarle FOR <hi>Jſhmael Rabſhacheh, A</hi> Cecropidan Lycaonite.</p>
            <p>BY S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. EDWARD HOBY, Knight, one of the <hi>Gentlemen of his Maieſties</hi> Priuie-Chamber.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Comitantur praelia praelum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Nath. Butter,</hi> by the Authoritie of Superiours. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:4324:2"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IOB 11.</hi> verſ. <hi>2.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Should not the multitude of wordes be anſwered? or ſhould a great talker be iuſtified?</p>
               <p>Should men hold their peace at thy lyes? and when thou mockeſt others, ſhall none make thee aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med?</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4324:2"/>
            <p>TO THE HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE, WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL, AND <hi>VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THY GENTLEMEN,</hi> The Students of the Law, in his Maieſties Innes of COVRT.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4324:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4324:3"/>
            <head>Thrice—Worthy Gentlemen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou are not to learne what <note n="a" place="margin">Artibus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietas ingenio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa caret.</note> 
               <hi>Artificiall</hi> ſhadowes <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie</hi> hath in all ages con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triued, for the couering of her <note n="b" place="margin">Monstrum horrendum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, ingens cui lumen ademptum.</note> vgly ſhape; neither are you vnable to diſcern the counterfeit colours wherwith ſhe hath varniſhed her <note n="c" place="margin">Reuelabo pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denda tua, in facie tua. <hi>Nahum. 3.5</hi>
               </note> wrinkled deformities, for the alluring of the giddie world to her banefull luſt. The truth is, ſhe hath ſo long forged, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the countenance of <hi>venerable Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> by her impious poſitions, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh practices, that her vſurping impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and impudent vſurpations, haue now iuſtly occaſioned, not only <hi>Church-men</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:4324:4"/>
to diſpute, but euen <hi>Lay-men</hi> to doubt of the authority of that Charter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with their fore-fathers were ſo groſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded. Hence it commeth to paſſe that finding her ſelf diſplumed of her wonted retinew, which ſhee is well-nigh out of hope to <note n="d" place="margin">Jctus Piſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor ſapit.</note> regaine, and depriued of thoſe naturall ſupplies, wherwith her ſtate was ſupported, &amp; her pompe maintained, ſhe now flieth abroad like a ſhrewiſh diſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted malecontent, in her frantique mood, <note n="e" place="margin">Vel vi, vel fraude valebo.</note> pulling, haling, ſpurning, ſcratching, and tearing al that ſtand in her <note n="f" place="margin">Aut inuentam aut ficiam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am.</note> way: yea bee they neuer ſo noble by diſcent, eminent in place, profound in Iudgement, skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in tongues, famous for learning, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, or experience in trauailes, if they <note n="g" place="margin">Laeſit qui non haeſit.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to dance a rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in her <hi>Orgions antick,</hi> ſhe will be ſure they ſhall not paſſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a broken head, or a black eye: witnes ſo many ſcurrilos &amp; ſcandalous Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets which haue of late bin ſcatterd; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in neither the highneſſe of ſacred Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, the matchleſſe gouernours of a well
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4324:4"/>
ſetled ſtate, nor the ſincere profeſſors of a ſpotleſſe truth, haue eſcaped without ſome vile blurr, and maleuolous aſperſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from one or other her ſuborned Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars and whifling agents: Neither hath their inraged malice, as yet vented all thoſe venemous crudities, wherwith their ſurfeited ſtomacks are ſurcharged, but as if they meant to make worke for a world of <hi>Galenists,</hi> and <hi>Paracelſians,</hi> they daily corrupt our pure ayre, by caſting out of that ſulphurious pit, no ſmall quantitie of their infectious dregs, and helliſh druggs, <note n="h" place="margin">Iras viuaces gerunt.</note> wherwith their vaine hope is, to caſt the ignorant, into a ſenceleſs ſleepe, and the learned into cauſeleſs diſgrace.</p>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong this <note n="i" place="margin">Brethren in euill. Gen. 49. v 15 <hi>Vaſa iniquita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis bellantia.</hi>
                  </note> fraternity, there is a freſh vpſtart, (vnto whom I preſume <hi>Pandoraes</hi> boxe was entayled) deſirous to bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. Hee is onely knowne vnto mee by the marke of <hi>I. R.</hi> but if I bee not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4324:5"/>
miſtaken in the <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Gen. 16 v. 15. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Eſa. 30.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Hierogliphicks,</hi> his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliars may ſalute him by the name of <hi>Iſhmael Rabſhacheh,</hi> he is ſo wholly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact of <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Gen. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> v. 9.</note> mocking and rayling, that hee well ſeemeth to haue the mixed quinteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of them both. This <hi>Polypragmiſt,</hi> forſooth, to ſhew his inuincible courage, and vndaunted ſpirit, (which I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe doth many miles outſtrip his leaden art, and heauy-heeld learning) hath vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken the Combat with one of your <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                     </hi> VV. Craſhaw.</note> 
                  <hi>Lecturers,</hi> and profeſſeth (as if his breaſt were the ſtore-houſe of <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> his medicinall receits) the preſent cure of all thoſe feſtered wounds, which were by him diſcouered, in the diſeaſed body of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church; little remembring, that <note n="n" place="margin">Roma iam ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us eſt malum.</note> old fleſh, &amp; inueterate ſores, require more then ordinary skil; and that it muſt bee a better tongue, then his mouth can yeild, to licke them whole. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, in this his preſumptious heat, his ſwelling and pregnant wit, hauing by the vvindie incurſion of ſuperiour
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4324:5"/>
hopes, conceiued the <hi>Idaea</hi> of an ill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potioned <hi>Brat,</hi> where-with for want of a good Mydwife he hath beene in trauaile theſe fiue yeares, is now at length deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of a little prettie <hi>Pygmie:</hi> whom, as if it had deſcended of the ſtock of <hi>Hercules,</hi> he hath chriſtned, <hi>The</hi> 
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Nil niſi bella crepat, bella, horrida bella.</note> 
                  <hi>ouerthrow of the Proteſtants pulpet Bables:</hi> and hath entred it into the <hi>Church-booke,</hi> to bee the worke of <hi>I. R.</hi> Rudent, (I ſhould ſay Student) in diuinity, <hi>Anno Domi.</hi> 1612. And, as if he had had the law on his ſide, he hath <note n="p" place="margin">Preface de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory.</note> inuited your worthy ſelues, <hi>the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Inns of Court,</hi> to the vpſitting. His hope, no doubt, is, that according to the law of Goſhipping, you will dandle the fathers none boy, and ſweare it is a iolly pretie ape. And ſo I proteſt you may: your verdite herein will not bee much amyſſe, for wot you what? he hath taught it, in leſſe then three monethes, to know mee better, then euer I knew my ſelfe. You would wonder to heare how in the liſping language it will name <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 7.</note> 
                  <hi>D.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4324:6"/>
Iewel,</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 7. 149</note> 
                  <hi>D. Andrews.</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 137.</note> 
                  <hi>D. Morton,</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 8.</note> 
                  <hi>D. Feild.</hi> 
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 85. 91 303.</note> 
                  <hi>Sir Edwyn Sands,</hi> and among the reſt <hi>Sir Edward Hoby,</hi> as if it had beene acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with either of vs, twice ſeauen yeares at the leaſt. Nay more then ſo, he hath breathed into it ſuch a Criticque, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretiue ſpirit, that it is able to controule, the valour, ſincerity, and learning of the beſt of vs all. But truſt me truely, it hath one propertie, which all this praemature forwardneſſe, is no waies able to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile: you will find it the moſt foule-mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed Impe, that euer <hi>Cerberus</hi> bred or <note n="x" place="margin">Tit. c. <hi>1.</hi> v. <hi>12</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Crete</hi> ſaw. Yet muſt I not conceale the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, which I haue in my own perticular reaped thereby, which is not much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, that which obliged <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 13</note> 
                  <hi>Gelon</hi> (of whom <hi>Aelian</hi> maketh mention) to his yolping Curre,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:4324:6"/>
               <head>§. 3.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His poore man, taking, (as it may ſeeme) an after-noones nap, fell into a very fearefull dreame, that his bowells were peirced with a thunder-bolte, the ſoddain and ghaſtly apprehenſion whereof, ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted him, that he ſent forth moſt piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful grones, in ſo much as his dog being not far off, and hearing the noyſe, fel on barking, till at lengh he quit his Maiſter, of his ſleepe and feare. Right ſo fared it with me, who thinking to repoſe my ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlatiue <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Vulnera vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neribus non ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das plura re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptis.</note> ſorrow, (for the loſſe of one onely Child, a vertuous and louing wife, a broken arme, a burning feuer, &amp; weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of eies, all in one yeare conglomera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) by the ſolace of a rurall deuoted <note n="a" place="margin">Deus nobis haec otia fecit.</note> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacy, fell, I know not how, to clyme the ſteepe hills of certaine craggy ſtudies, and vnwonted ſpeculations, and had not the belowing of this roaring <note n="b" place="margin">Ouid. Met. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Lycaonite,</hi> ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what awakened mee, it is twenty to one, I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4324:7"/>
had bin no leſſe perplexed with <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Printed at Venice. 1593.</note> 
                  <hi>Arca Noe,</hi> then <hi>Gelon</hi> with his diſmal dream. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhould I much degenerate from my ſelf, if in leiw hereof, I would not vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe a litle conference with him, whoſe cal hath freed my braine from ſo great a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, And ſeeing he refers him-ſelf to the cenſure of your learned ſociety, of whoſe noble diſpoſition, and renowned diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, your nuptiall reuells, and graue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings haue giuen ſufficient teſtimony, to the admyring world, I cannot repute it, the leſt part of my hapines, that I am ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to anſwer, at ſo honorable abench, againſt thoſe vniuſt Cauills and <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> eſt morſus fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us, qui ſape, fraude, vel vrbanitate regitur vt aliud ſonet, aliud in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligatur. Macrob.</note> ſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matizing imputations, which this falſefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note n="e" place="margin">Ouid. Met. lib. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Cecropidan</hi> hath forged, againſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine paſſages, in a ſhort letter of mine, which ſome few yeares ſince, paſt from my pen <note n="f" place="margin">To Ma. T. H.</note> to the preſse. And here, before I enter the liſt, I muſt deſire you, to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that my purpoſe is not to foreſtal <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>M. Craſhaws</hi> market, nor to put my ſic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle into his harueſt, I doubt not but hee
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4324:7"/>
hath ſtore of ſtrong powders to mak him feele the ſmart of thoſe wounds, which by drawing ouer a faire skin, he ſeeks to hide, and his Quiuer full of ſuch forked ſhaftes, for the entring of the weake ſides, of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> cauſe, that the beſt chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, in the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> Hoſpitall, ſhall hardly with all the art they haue, bee ſo hardy as to pluck them out. So far am I from vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the leaſt part of his praiſe, that it grieus me to think, he ſhold waſte his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vpon ſo inglorious a <note n="h" place="margin">Hic cum vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus erittecum certaſſe feretur</note> foe. The only ſtraite that I am in, is, in reſpect of my ſelf, how I ſhould wade through with your good opinion, being to ſute my <hi>Apology</hi> to the <hi>Iſhmalites</hi> obiections, whereof ſome are perſonall, and cannot be well anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by my ſelfe <note n="i" place="margin">Nec te collau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des nec te cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paueris ipſe.</note> without apparance of vainglorious oſtentation, and ſome ſo friuolous, that I haue little or no vſe of thoſe my ſmale readings, which in a more materiall cauſe, I mought with greater pleaſure to my ſelfe, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps content to you, haue imployed;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4324:8"/>
But becauſe I am ſingled out, onely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend my ſelfe, I muſt craue your forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in this, till my fitter opportunitie inhable mee to repay your patience in a better kinde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>§. 4.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt <hi>Epithite</hi> with which it pleaſeth this <hi>Hagueren</hi> to grace thoſe my curſory lines is, the friendly cenſure, of <note n="k" place="margin">Preface dedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>catory. pag. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>an vnlearned letter,</hi> as if him-ſelfe were <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Act. 8.9.</hi> Habet quenda acul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melia, quem pati prudentes as viri boni difficillimé poſſunt.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſuch a one as had by his labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous induſtry, climed the top of <hi>Pernaſſus,</hi> and drunke the fountaine of <hi>Helicon</hi> drie: the triall hereof I referre, to the vnparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all reader.</p>
               <p>Indeed I cannot but ingenuouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that I haue loſt many <note n="m" place="margin">Hoeſcio, quod nihil Scio</note> howers, which I would be glad with double pains, and greater price to redeeme: yet haue I not beene ſuch a ſtranger to thoſe ſacred Siſters, but that I haue ſeene <hi>Aristotles</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:4324:8"/>
Well, and friendly conuerſed with them all. And were it not that <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ide.</hi> §. 3.</note> my infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties did ſuppreſſe the virility of my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, I could perhaps readily ſhew <hi>(abſit inuidia verbo)</hi> as many of their fauors, as this boaſting <hi>Iſhmaelite,</hi> yea ſhould hee ſeeke and ſearch all the corners of his deske. Had any approued <hi>Artiſt,</hi> laid ignorance to my charge, I ſhould the ſooner haue ſuſpected my ſelfe; but when your wiſdomes ſhall peruſe the <note n="o" place="margin">Si ego dignus hac centume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, tu indignus qui faceres ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> 
                  <hi>Solaeciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes,</hi> crabbed phraſes, and incongruities of this nibling Probationer, I doubt not but the compariſon will purchaſe my <hi>Nullitie,</hi> the title of <note n="p" place="margin">Mediocria firma.</note> 
                  <hi>Mediocritie.</hi> In the entrance of his preface, which may ſerue as a Perſpectiue to the reſt, hee caſts a <hi>Fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure,</hi> and rayſeth ſuch a number of <hi>iffs,</hi> that <hi>Barbariſme</hi> it ſelfe, would bluſh to reade them. If (ſaith hee) <hi>many ſeduced ſoules in our (in this reſpect,) vnhappy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. &amp;c. If if, &amp;c.</hi> Heare is a iob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing Parentheſis, and a crabbed ſtrayne indeed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:4324:9"/>In this my learned <hi>Magnificoe,</hi> ſhowes what refined ſtuffe we ſhall meete withal, in ſifting the ſequele of his diſcourſe: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a good mans dog, hath broken his leg ouer a leſſe ſtyle. Now if I ſhould ſpell all his iffs backwards, and turne them into ſo many <note n="q" place="margin">Phi. nota fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris.</note> fyes, I might cry, fy vpon thoſe <note n="r" place="margin">Telas arane arum texuit.</note> 
                  <hi>Cobweb</hi> alluſions, ſo often iterated, that the margent would not contain, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Pages, wherein the <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 4.20.22. <hi>fower times.</hi> 31 36.50.57.58.59.133.</note> 
                  <hi>Spyder</hi> or <hi>Flye</hi> is praedomina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Fy vpon your <hi>accidental &amp; genericall</hi> chriſtening of <note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 246.</note> 
                  <hi>Bells</hi> and relatiue honor of<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 201.</note> Images. Fy vpon the bird that defiles his owne neſt, terming his country an <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>vnhappy kingdom,</hi> the Climat <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 36.</note> 
                  <hi>Clow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, &amp; infamous,</hi> the <hi>ayre groſſe,</hi> and this I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſland an <hi>vſurper</hi> of the ſurname of <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Crete. Fy</hi> vpon that blockiſh ſimplicity, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds a rhethorical acclamation, which the Prophet vſeth to the <note n="a" place="margin">Eſay. 45. v. 8.</note> Clowdes, and a theological inuocation, which the Papiſts direct to the woden <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 207.</note> Croſſe: not diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing betweene a <hi>Hyperbolicall exagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and a Superstitious obſecration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:4324:9"/>The like art he vſeth vnder the priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of a ſimple Metaphor, to diuide the kingdom between God, and <note n="c" place="margin">The throne of mercy is hers by a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor. <hi>pag.</hi> 168.</note> the Virgin. Deſerues hee not to haue your voices for the Rhethoricke Lecture? Thus might I ſtuffe much paper, with many like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauoury <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 40.</note> Baberies, wherwith being <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 52</note> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorpt, in his <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 44.</note> extaticall contemplations, he perfumeth his il current and worſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent lines. So that hee doth well to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioine the reading of his imaginary refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation as a <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 50.</note> pennance to your iudicious eyes; neither haue you any reaſon to ſtop him with a <hi>Nil minus,</hi> when in plaine tearms he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth, <note n="h" place="margin">P. <hi>50.</hi> Ex ore tuo te iudico.</note> 
                  <hi>Factus ſum inſipiens,</hi> I am become a foole; vnder this colour of affected ſimplicity, his deſire is to paſſe, for <hi>Tom tell troth,</hi> that ſo with his fooles boltes hee might <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 14.</note> cracke in peeces the credit of our Engliſh Church: But albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it hee ſlauer my poore letter, with his dri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueling tearmes, I wil yet do him his right, ſince hee will needes bee a foole, I dare vndertake you ſhall finde him a crafty
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4324:10"/>
foole. When any of their owne aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Records are produced, he hath a trick to turne them oft in a trice, blearing his Reader, that theſe are but <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 7 23.</note> 
                  <hi>worme-eaten ſayings of an old gloſſe:</hi> when they are char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with lying ſtories, painted in their Chappels, that fault hee layes to the <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Paynters</hi> penſil, and when they are vrged with idolatrous appeale, from God to the Virgine, and the like abſurdities, hee ſhifts them off to the <note n="m" place="margin">P. <hi>37.</hi> Picto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Poetis.</note> 
                  <hi>Poets</hi> pen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>§. 5.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus doth he with the long ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded skirts of his fooles coat, thinke ſhiftingly to hide that, which he dares not doctrinal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defend: betweene Poets and Painters he challengeth licence for his Church, to teach and write what ſhee liſt, without check and controle. Which idle conceit, hath ſo fully poſſeſſed them, that there are fewe, or none of their late VVriters, who haue not beene free, of one, or both
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4324:10"/>
thoſe (ſo largely priuiledged) companies. Their boundleſſe, and groundleſſe ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, bewray the moſt to be either Poets, or Paynters; when their Church Hymns are confeſſed to be but <hi>figuratiue</hi> Poems, and Poeticall fancies, and their pictures but <hi>Paynters</hi> deuices, you may gheſſe of the inſolidity of the reſt.</p>
               <p>I feare <hi>Rabſhachehs</hi> 
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Fy vpon a ſloud of fools.</note> fooles coate, will be well clawed by his Superiors, for tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of tales out of ſchooles, as alſo for diſcountenancing their highly eſteemed <note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 208.</note> 
                  <hi>Breuiaries,</hi> and <note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 156.</note> 
                  <hi>Councells:</hi> And he well deſerues it, as being the moſt brazen fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced intrudor, that <hi>Fooliana</hi> euer harbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. You would wonder how he ſhould lurke in the <hi>Parliament</hi> houſe, to publiſh our (ſuppoſed) <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 59.</note> commaunds. Is it not ſtrange, that a principall <note n="r" place="margin">Earle of Saliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</note> 
                  <hi>Secretarie</hi> of ſo great a ſtate, ſhould let fall to ſuch an open mouthed fellow, his diſlike, and reſolution to diſcarde <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 52</note> Maſter <hi>Craſhawes</hi> Sermon, as our <hi>Cecropidan,</hi> peraduenture, to raiſe ſome ſiniſter ſuſpition, pretends.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4324:11"/>
Were he now aliue to heare thoſe new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented fictions, I wonder what he would thinke of ſuch poring ſpies, and hollow-harted Intelligencers <note n="t" place="margin">M. Tom. Dyrre.</note>Did a Courtier of my acquaintance, who is not far behind him for learning, heare him aſ-certain ſo much, I ſmile to thinke how hee would looke. I preſume the afore-ſaid Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor would ſoone caſt a net to catch this fleeting Gudgeon, that makes himſelfe ſo priuy to his inward thoughts: And yet (though by all likelihood hee is not <note n="u" place="margin">Out of the current of his natiue ſtreams</note> 
                  <hi>extra quatuor Maria</hi>) this would not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be compaſſed, For if euer any fellow were made of quick-ſiluer, this is he, as I verily thinke. One while he is in <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 322.</note> 
                  <hi>Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> and can tell you what peaſe-pottage (tawny) the Miniſter did eate, whileſt his fellowes vvere fighting. An other vvhile hee is at an execution at <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 106.</note> 
                  <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and by and by he conuerſeth with a <note n="z" place="margin">P. <hi>321.</hi> Credite Piſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> 
                  <hi>Gentleman</hi> of Honour, vvho bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him nevves from my Lord <hi>De la Warres</hi> ovvne mouth: Nay, there can no
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4324:11"/>
ſooner bee an argument propounded at my table, but hee hath it ſtraight by the end. If he be now amongſt the roaring <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 100.</note> 
                  <hi>Rakehile,</hi> in the Colledge pumpe, he will in a moment bee inuiſible, among the Goſſippes in <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 185. 245</note> 
                  <hi>Pemblico:</hi> It is not vnlike hee hath met with <hi>Fortunatus</hi> his hat, his eares are as quicke, as his thought, and his pen ſo well feathered, that it follows him cloſe at the heeles: whatſoeuer his <hi>Philautie</hi> preſenteth, his heart crediteth, and his hand publiſheth.</p>
               <p>Among many other his imaginarie diſcoueries, hee would faine make vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that hee hath beene with <hi>(glorious)</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Pag. <hi>104.</hi> Qui vbique nullibi</note> Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> ghoſt, taking vpon him to determine with what conſorts ſhee is accompanied; and as if hee had a priuy key to the cloſet of your hearts, hee is ſo ſhameleſly audacious, as vnder colour of rumor, to ſound a falſe Alarum, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming his Readers, that <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 5.</note> your gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diſlike, of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Craſhawes</hi> intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancie in writing, and folly in marrying,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4324:12"/>
(being held no conuenient qualitie for your Preacher) did praeſage his preſent diſcharge from his office. Is not this a daungerous mate, that hath ſuch a num<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber of Familiars, to ſend into euery <note n="e" place="margin">But Picke. hatch, Bedlam Shorditch. <hi>Pag.</hi> 276.</note> coaſt? Can hee bee ſo carefull of your Honors, as hee pretends, that broacheth out of his fuſtie braine, ſuch muſty ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dales, for the vilifying of your iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and traducing the conſtancie of your faith? No maruaile if hee taxe my learning, vvho laies ſo hard a cenſure vpon the bleſſed ſoule, of ſo worthy a Saint, chargeth a great Counſellor of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and your venerable Societie, with theſe ſurmiſes; were that time beſtowed in his theologicall ſtudies, which hee ſpends in hunting after fabulous reports, hee might with more probability, haue made a greater breach into our Fort, then hee is now with his paper-ſhot like to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:4324:12"/>
               <head>§. 6.</head>
               <p>YEt I cannot but commend him for his iugling, what hee wants in reall, hee ſupplies vvith perſonall impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: I haue eaten more then a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhell of ſalt in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> the <hi>Lowe-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, Spaine, Portugal,</hi> &amp;c. in all vvhich time I cannot iuſtly accuſe my ſelfe of any military ſeruice, by ſea or land which I refuſed, or diſhonorable diſgrace which I pocquetted: Yet doth this <hi>Lycaonite,</hi> for vvant of better ſtuffe, diſplay mee to be a Knight, <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 21.</note> 
                  <hi>more famous for my penne, then my ſworde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It ſeems he grieues that I ſhould ſleepe in a ſound skinne; the truth is, as I was neuer forward in putting my ſelfe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the pikes of needeleſſe daungers; ſo did I neuer turne my backe, where my aduerſarie durſt ſhevv his face. <note n="g" place="margin">Sua vulnera narrat.</note> 
                  <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les glorioſus,</hi> beene long ſince a laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtocke, to the vvhole Theatre:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4324:13"/>
I haue euer held it more valour to let o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers feele, then for my ſelfe to make boaſt of the ſharpeneſſe of my ſworde. If I haue not beene famous for quarrels, it hath either been my happineſſe, which hee ſeemeth to enuy, or my heedineſſe, vvhich hee hath reaſon to commend. Whether <hi>Mars</hi> or <hi>Mercury</hi> had the prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominance in my Natiuity, I am not ſo cunning <note n="h" place="margin">Format enim natura prius no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>intus ad omnem fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> a Starre-gazer to determine. It ſhall bee my greateſt content, to ſtand as a <note n="i" place="margin">Jſti adſimiles ſunt abacorum calculis, qui &amp; ſecucdum vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem Cal culatoris modo obolum aere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, modò, talentum va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci ad nutum Principis, mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dò beati, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dò miſerifi un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Cypher,</hi> in what ranke of em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment my Maſters fauour ſhall bee pleaſed to place mee: To whoſe honor, and ſeruice, I will neuer be daunted to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice my deareſt blood. How this <hi>Rodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantado</hi> may vnderualew my worth, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe hee were a more competent Iudge, the matter is not great.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:4324:13"/>
               <head>§. 7.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Is next flurte is at my witt, which (ſaith hee) <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>pag</hi> 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Were it aunſwerable to my name, or my learning, as high, as my own conceite thereof, I were a ſoaring birde.</hi> Thus do his ſquibbes flie about to ſindge my feathers. By all meanes I would not haue him loſe this conceit. Marke the alluſion: <hi>were my wit aunſwerable to my name, I were a ſoaring bird:</hi> Well flowne <hi>Buzzard:</hi> I perceiue hee will flie farre for a ieſt: would hee not proue (think you) a good <hi>Anagram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt,</hi> that can deſcant ſo well vppon a name? Well I am glad I had it for him, or elſe all this ſport had beene mar'd. To iuſtifie my witte, were wit-leſſe folly; Yet if an ambitious ſpirit, had that little in keeping, I am perſwaded hee ſhould haue no great neede, to borrow of this indigent Artiſt: who would make
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4324:14"/>
vs beleeue he was borne in the ful moone, when wit was a dealing. The fates, no doubt, were very partiall, to emptie all their vyalls, into one caske; It cannot be but he muſt needs haue a great skonce, that hath ingroſſed ſuch a maſſe of wit. There is no queſtion but this <hi>Brauo</hi> will wel perform the gybing task, vnto which by the <hi>Ladies</hi> liberall purſe—promiſes (their former <note n="l" place="margin">Spreta exoleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuat, ſi iraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care, aguita videntur. c. Tacit.</note> Libels being turned into ſmoake) he ſtands ingaged. If hee miſſe his pay let him ſobbe for <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>I. R.</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth me, ſhe was of the arting kinds.</note> her death, who hauing giuen firſt incouragement, did not long after, by Gods great mercy, ende her daies in a farre other manner, then he expected.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:4324:14"/>
               <head>§. 8.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He conceipt of my lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, wherewith my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent thoughts are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly vpbrayded, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee well remoued by bare words; but had hee a window into my breaſt, to ſurvaie the imaginations of my heart, his pen is not now ſo buſie in cenſuring, as his tongue would bee dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in reuoking. I am, God wot, too pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy to mine owne defects, to giue credit to any comparatiue attributes in that kinde. My deſire hath bin to holde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity herein, to my firſt breeding, and to keepe pace, with men of my owne ranke. Wherein, if I haue gayned ſo much as may ſerue for my owne medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and my Countries affayres, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I am intereſſed, I neither enuy them that haue more, nor diſparrage thoſe which haue leſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:4324:15"/>Whervpon this his ſurmize ſhould grow, I cannot readily tell, vnleſſe he find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe wrung with his owne <note n="n" place="margin">Obtrectator magis m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rbum ſuum quam mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res alienos pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</note> ſhooe. Had I as much learning as hee wants, I could finde good vſe for much more. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle long ſince taught me, and lent me a brydle, which may ſerue as a curbe, to ſubdue the like motions of his ſwelling pride: <note n="o" place="margin">1. Cor. 3 <hi>v.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Si quis ſe exiſtimat ſcire aliquid, nondum cognouit, quemadmodum oporteat eum ſcire.</hi> The greateſt Tympany hath not alwaies the beſt burthen; where the hill is higheſt, commonly, the graſſe is loweſt; the deepeſt riuer runnes with the leaſt noice, <hi>Sapere ſupra ſobrietatem,</hi> 
                  <note n="p" place="margin">O di pracocia ingenia.</note> hath beene as dangerous in the Church, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious in the ſtate. A great Maſt ſoone ouerturnes a little Barke, and hee which bringeth a great Armie into the field, without victuall or munition, is like to goe by the worſte. Wherefore, how-ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer I may be miſconſtrued, my courſe hath euer beene, by comparing that which I doe not know, with that little
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4324:15"/>
which I haue attained, to ſubſtract ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ounces, from that ordinary opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which men of his profeſſion doe in like caſe intertaine. It is for children to bee proude of Peacocks feathers, and for baſe aſpiring ſpirits, to ſet out their paynted butter-flies with Eagles winges.</p>
               <p>True generoſity baniſheth ſuch baſe thoughts, if the <note n="q" place="margin">Vino vendibili non o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dera.</note> wine bee good, no matter for a greene buſh. Wherfore I am well content to beſtow this Cauill vpon the firſt <note n="r" place="margin">Plaerique in id nati, vt ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi quieſcant, nec alios ſinant. Thucid.</note> founder, for his paines If his meanes may bee bettered, or his credit more currant, by the ſtampe which it ſhal receuie, from the partial hand of his ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weening imagination, I ſhall not repine to ſee him make his beſt of ſuch ordinary commodities. The world will perhaps wonder at my charity, and the rather for that hee further taxeth mee for, <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 22.</note> 
                  <hi>flut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering in a webbe of weake ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unders,</hi> which is ſo vile a reproach, that patience it ſelfe would ſhrinke, if not ſinke, vnder the burthen.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:4324:16"/>A man had neede haue the ſheilde of <hi>Pallas</hi> to repell theſe poyſoned dartes: but as longe as they flie from ſo weake a hand, without the vantage of firmer proofes, there is good hope they will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fly flarre, nor peirce deepe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>§. 9.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat hee ſhould meane by theſe weake ſlaunders, my dull brayne cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, vnleſſe he haue refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to thoſe three <hi>Falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications,</hi> where-with his ſeditious treatiſe, would gladly perſwade <hi>Saint Auguſtine</hi> to finde him-ſelfe greiued. <note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 134.</note> 
                  <hi>This</hi> (ſaith he) is not onely, <hi>groſe ignorance, but alſo great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudency, &amp;c. Want of conſcience, which I haue bewraied, in framing ſentences for Sainst Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin; which he neither wrote, nor ſo much as dreamed of.</hi> And therfore he warnes Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Craſhawe</hi> that, in <hi>proofe of his aſſertion,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4324:16"/>
hee bring not ſuch testimony as the three alleaged by me, out of that Father, to proue he reiected the Machabees.</hi> Thus doth this Spider-catcher trauaiſe his ground, with a goodly flouriſh, as if he meant, with the weake Goddeſſes, to binde <hi>Iupiter:</hi> but if he bring not ſome <hi>Briareus</hi> to aſſiſte him, it wil not be long ere he be <note n="u" place="margin">Magn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is tamen excidit auſis.</note> out of breath. Amongſt all that I wrote in an 114, <hi>pages,</hi> hee hath only a ſpite at one leafe, which lies in the heart of my letter; and that the world may know hee is a man of his handes, hee puts euery ſillable to the ſword. One ſhall hardly finde ſuch an Examiner in a country. I beſhrew his curioſity; Hee is ſo nice, that hee hath made Mee and my Printer allmoſt fall out, about ſetting <note n="x" place="margin">Pag. <hi>135.</hi> Grande piacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum.</note> 
                  <hi>Razis</hi> for <hi>Razias.</hi> The beſt ſatiſfaction I could get from him was, that if Maſter <hi>Iſhmael</hi> be ſo ſtrict for a letter, rather then he would ſtand in law with him, he would willingly graunt that laſt ſillable, to <note n="y" place="margin">Nunquam ego hominem ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis aſinam vidi</note> him and his heires for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:4324:17"/>This is he by way of amends content to ſet downe vnder his hand. And that you may ſee hee meanes no double dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, he is well pleaſed, the whole world ſhould be witneſſe: adding this proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he is ſorry he hath withheld his due ſo longe. But to return to that Marble pillar, that glorious Saint, that euer admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> I cannot but deplore my hard hap, that I ſhould be indited for the leaſt wronge, done to him, to whoſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Meditations, ſweet ſayings, and learned diſcourſes, I owe more then the half of my ſelf. Would any man beleeue, that I ſhold father that booke, <hi>de mirabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſacrae ſcripturae</hi> vpon him?<note n="z" place="margin">Pag. <hi>122.</hi> Varius ait, Scaurus negat.</note> 
                  <hi>Rabſhacbeh</hi> auerres that. Indeed I cannot denie that finding it in their owne Coppies in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall rancke, with thoſe other bookes that goe vnder the title of <hi>Saint Auguſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> his workes, and hauing no other certaine, or knowne author, vnder whoſe name I mought cite it, I was loath to trouble the margent, with any
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4324:17"/>
Circumloquution, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenting my ſelf on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to note where it might be found. And this I did to a double end. Firſt, to draw and extort from the aduerſarie, an open confeſſion of the falſehood of their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, in packing and placing their ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardly brood, amongſt the naturall chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and true branches of thoſe <hi>Angelical</hi> Doctors. Which vniuſt dealing, hath not beene the leaſt bane of the Chriſtian world. Secondly, to inferre vpon their owne acknowledgement, and diſcarding this booke, that the teſtimonie euen of the moſt partiall, that vented their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies in thoſe firſt declining yeeres, will ſteed them but very little, for authorizing the <hi>Machabees,</hi> from whence the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of their praier, and oblation for the dead was firſt deriued. As neere as I can remember, I thus argued with my ſelfe: If they grant that Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> penne doe feuer the <hi>Machabees</hi> from the diuine Canon, then the matter will bee ſoone at an end: and if they deny that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4324:18"/>
booke to bee his, then hovv vvill they excuſe the infidelitie of their Church, who hath in her time plaide manie ſuch lewde prankes as this? Or how vvill they anſwere Antiquitie, vvhich diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed theſe bookes eight hundred and nine yeeres; before either <note n="a" place="margin">The book <hi>de Mirabilibus,</hi> was written 627. <hi>vt. P.</hi> 133</note> 
                  <hi>Luther</hi> or <hi>Suinglius</hi> vvere borne.</p>
               <p>So that my reply is this: If it bee a booke of no account, not ſauouring of Saint <hi>Augustines</hi> vvit, learning, and ſtile, then are they culpable either of forging, or maintenance, or both; If it bee not his, why was it entertained? vvhy is it continued in their own editions amongſt his golden works? If they print it vnder his name, they may giue me leaue ſo to note it, where they might be ſure to finde it. Yea, but<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 3. q. 45. <hi>art.</hi> 3. <hi>ad</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>teſte Tho. Aquinate,</hi> it hath beene long ſince pronounced diſcarded: By like it will not ſerue the Popes turne; vvhy then welfare their honeſt <hi>Index ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgatorius,</hi> that will tell manie tricks of the like cleanly conueiance. In what an
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:4324:18"/>
intricate age doe wee liue? A man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, ſafely, read any their fathers, but he muſt turne ouer <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> before hee can tell what workes are their owne; and conſequently, may catch a Snake, inſtead of an Eele, ere hee be aware.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>§. 10.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus you well ſee <hi>(ingenuous Gentlemen)</hi> how I haue quit my hands of the firſt falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, my ſcope being not then to prooue that booke <hi>de mirabilibus</hi> to be Saint <hi>Auguſtines,</hi> but firſt to euince them of forgerie, and then to ſhevve vvhat their ovvne Antiquitie did manie hundred yeeres agoe thinke, of thoſe <hi>Apocriphall</hi> books. Had I bin in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed perſwaded, that it had bin S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stines</hi> owne off-ſpring, I ſhould haue held it needles to cumber the breuity of a letter with more then one other proofe of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4324:19"/>
ſame Father<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But becauſe I foreſaw, that by this baite I ſhould bring the oppoſite partie, to one of thoſe ineuitable diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantages formerly mentioned; I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore added tvvo ſeuerall teſtimonies, (vvhich he cannot diſauow) to confirme the ſame truth; in the alleaging vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, hee cries out, <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 134.</note> 
                  <hi>that I am a notorious falſefier.</hi> For triall vvherof my pen pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates it ſelfe to your cenſure.</p>
               <p>The vvords by mee cited are theſe; <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> T. H. P. <hi>60.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Machabaeorum Scriptura recepta est ab Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia, non inutiliter, ſi ſobriè legatur, vel auditatur, maxime propter iſtos Martyres:</hi> vvhereupon my inference was this, <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go ob hanc cauſam in Canone morum, non fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei cenſeri poſset.</hi> Which laſt clauſe I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how it ſhould ſo paſſe my ſight in the re-vievv: For, peruſing my firſt draught, I finde <hi rend="sup">go</hi> vvritten ſhort in another let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to diſtinguiſh my inference from his proofe; It ſeemeth either my Manua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties haſte, or the <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dominum De um<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>strum Papam,</hi> not his Phraſe but ouer-ſight in print. <hi>P.</hi> 149.</note> Printers miſpriſion, hath turned <hi>go</hi> into <hi>(ſed)</hi> as if the ſame
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:4324:19"/>
had beene continued, vvhereas my Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh reddition was plaine. <hi>And that (conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently) they are in the Canon of Manners, &amp;c.</hi> vvhich Aduerbe, their former error cauſed them vtterly to omit. <note n="f" place="margin">Verſtij Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſceue.</note> Such ſcapes oftentimes happen, when the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor himſelfe cannot attend the preſſe. Now that you may perceiue there is no ſuch Trophey in this caſuall addition, which no man of ſence vvould willingly haue ſuffered, when the Authors are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious to euery eye; you ſhall ſee, I had S. <hi>Hieroms</hi> authority for that inference, though I then did not quote him, whoſe words are theſe:</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Jn praf. lib. Salomonis.</note>
                  <hi>Iudith, Tobiae, et Machabaeorum libros le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git quidem Eccleſia, ſed eos inter Canonicas Scriptur as non recepit:</hi> and hee explaines himſelfe how this ſhould be vnderſtood, <hi>Legat Eccleſia,</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>ad aedificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem plebis, non ad authoritatem dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Eccleſiaſticorum confirmandam;</hi> rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon all theſe together you ſhall find them amount to no leſſe ſumme, then that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:4324:20"/>
the bookes of <hi>Machabees</hi> are in <hi>Canone morum, non fidei, cenſendi.</hi> Might it haue pleaſed him to haue ſifted <hi>Lyra, Brito, Rabanus,</hi> and <hi>Caietan,</hi> vvhom I there cited, this matter would not haue beene ſuch a beame in his eye.</p>
               <p>How will he looke when M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Craſhaw</hi> ſhal make him fly to his Printer for Sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuarie in greater extremities, then the miſtaking of a word? Will you giue me leaue to praeſage vvhat he will ſay? Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this clauſe annexed be true in it ſelfe; yet how can it bee collected out of theſe former words, when as S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> ſhewing that the <hi>Iewes</hi> doe not admit the booke of <hi>Machabees,</hi> as they do the Law, Prophets, and Pſalmes, addeth <hi>Sed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta eſt ab Eccleſia non inutiliter, ſi ſobriè legatur, vel audiatur, maximè propter iſtos Martyres Machabaeos;</hi> How can you then conclude, <hi>ergo, it is not Canonicall?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay rather, the conſequence will be this, <hi>ergo the Chriſtian Church doth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the booke of</hi> Machabees, <hi>as Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:4324:20"/>
in that ſenſe, that the Iewes did refuſe them, to wit as the Lawe, Prophets, and Pſalmes, any of</hi> 
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 135.</note> 
                  <hi>which may more hurt then profit, if the ſame bee read in a drunken fit of a wanton wit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This inference I grant is in another letter indeed, his Printer hath done him right to ſet it in his owne Character; for neither did Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> dreame, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would any ſober ſetled braine ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vpon ſuch a ſenſe. Doth not hee make Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeake that which hee neuer meant, vvhen hee rackes his words, inforcing him to ſay that <hi>Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Scripture is receiued of the Church, with a Si,</hi> which is neceſſarily to bee acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, though it fall out by default to bee <hi>Sapor mortis ad mortem?</hi> or did hee dreame of ſuch a drunken Church, as theirs ſeems to be by their cloyning of the Scriptures from the common people, leaſt it ſhould hurt them? Had his purpoſe bin to ſet theſe books in the ſame throne imperiall vvith the ſacred Scriptures,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:4324:21"/>
to vvhat end dooth he inſtance in, thoſe <hi>Machabees</hi> Martyrs? This ſpecificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>(maximè propter iſtos Martyres Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabaeos)</hi> declares vvhere the daunger lies: implying, if vvee ſayle vvell by theſe rocks, there is (though no neceſſity) ſome vſe of the reſt. So that the words, rightly poyſed vvill beare that diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, vvhich Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> vvho was better acquainted vvith Saint <hi>Augustines</hi> meaning, and the Churches cuſtome, dooth reſolutely maintaine, that <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall</hi> Scripture muſt neceſſarilie bee receiued: as for other vncertaine wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, they may not vnprofitablie bee read:</p>
               <p>And whereas hee confeſſeth that the <hi>Iewes,</hi> vvho were the beſt Surueyors of the authority of their ovvne Hiſtories, did reiect them; You may well thinke, hee held it ſmall reaſon for after ages to intertaine them in the higheſt eſteeme, as Iudges of their faiths: though hee ſaw many good things, for which the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4324:21"/>
Church, with a little caution, did approue them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>§. 11.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus for want of better ſporte, this trifling companion, is faine to play with a feather, which when he hath blown vp as high as hee can, falls downe, and ſtickes vpon his owne coate: I cannot blame you if your <note n="i" place="margin">Angligena at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollant equites, pedites<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinnum.</note> laughter ſome-what paſſe modeſty, when you conſider how wittely he workes, vpon that clauſe, <hi>Si ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brié legatur,</hi> turning the weakenes of the iudgement (which <hi>Saint Augustine</hi> vpon good probability feared) into that intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance of diſordered affection, which was not by him intended. By this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon acceptation of the word <hi>Sobriè</hi> (in this place ridiculous) hee glides to this needleſſe concluſion, <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 135.</note> 
                  <hi>that there is no ſtory, nor miracle in the holy Bible, which ſome will not deride, when they bibble, and take</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:4324:22"/>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Faeda Tobacci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeriquid vult contagio ſum, Prater inau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditam perlus membre lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m?</note> 
                  <hi>Tobacco, or when they read the Scripture, as Sir</hi> Edward Hoby <hi>doth ſeeme to doe</hi> Lypſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us <hi>his booke, of our Ladies miracles by the fier ſide, when men roaſt crabs to driue à man out of à melancholy fitt;</hi> 
                  <note n="m" place="margin">To M. <hi>T. H. Pag.</hi> 102.</note> I preſume you haue read that diſcourſe, ſo that I ſhall not need twiſe to preſent you with the ſame diſh. Neuer did your eies behold ſuch lewd lies, and incredible falſe-hoods, as that <note n="n" place="margin">Aliquando fit in Ecleſia max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ima deceptio populi in mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis ſactis à Sacerdotibus propter lucrum L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a. in. ca. <hi>14.</hi> Daniel.</note> Miracle-monger ſetteth to ſale for ſound truthes. It is not vnlike, that this probationer hath taken vp ſome ſtore of them vpon truſt, and becauſe he cannot now ſo cleanly put them to ſale, but that they ſtill he vpon his hand, (the dulleſt ſent finding that they haue taken too much winde,) hee therefore takes it in dudgeon that I ſhould hinder his market by ſaying that <note n="o" place="margin">Reddere perſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nae ſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cenue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nientia cui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>.</note> 
                  <hi>Lypſius is worthy the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by the fier ſide, when men roast crabbs.</hi> This makes him as hotte as a toſte. This roaſting of Crabbs ſettes his teeth on edge.</p>
               <p>Doe you ſee what a queaſie ſtomack
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:4324:22"/>
hee hath? His <note n="p" place="margin">Et data Roma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nis venia eſt in digna poet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Poets and Painters may lymme and faine, what ridiculous <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeras</hi> they pleaſe, by vertue of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation; But Sir <hi>Edward Hoby</hi> muſt be called in queſtion, if hee chance to clap a <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erba<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> praeui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam rem non inuita ſequun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur.</note> wilde phraſe vpon a vile fiction: As if I were now to learne of ſuch an <hi>Hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didaſcalian Paedagogue to</hi> 
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Quo ſcribi poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt numero, quoue ordine dicam.</note> 
                  <hi>meaſure my</hi> phraſe by his <note n="ſ" place="margin">Sibi conuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia fingit.</note> rule and line. Alaſſe poore Nouice, I haue liued a little too longe to goe to ſchoole to ſuch an <hi>Ignatius</hi> as hee is, that cannot diſtinguiſh between a Helmet, and a Couentry capp. I haue euer held it art enough, for mee to pleaſe my <note n="t" place="margin">Quem penes arbitrium est, et ius, et forma loquendi.</note> ſelfe; It is for ſuch ſeruile pens as his, to write in Moode and Figure: But doth hee not (thinke you) deſerue the wood of the Crabb, that is ſo angry with the Crab of the wood? Can you deny that hee flutters in a web of fooliſh Baberies, when he bables of <hi>bibling &amp; taking</hi> 
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Nuga mea arguuntur, adeó factorum inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens ſum.</note>
                  <hi>Tobac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co.</hi> I am ſure this is no mortal ſin, though if it were, I haue litle reaſon to trauel to the <hi>Popes</hi> toe for a Pardon, no not if I were
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4324:23"/>
ſure to haue the paring of his nayle with th' appurtenances for my paines. Shall I be ſo bold as to make you my confeſſors? Then I confeſſe in my time I haue not beene an enemy to that <hi>Indian</hi> weede, and perhaps haue ſpent ſome-what that way, which had bin better giuen to the poore. Yet my tennants cannot ſay, but that my chimneys did euer ſmoak more then my noſe. As for theſe late yeares, I doe not remember, that I had a pipe in my hand twice. So that the Informer may put vp this ieſt in his boxe; If he be as free from all his olde vices, and drunken conceites, as I am from this vanity, hee ſhall not neede any great pennance. You may ſee how gladly hee would finde a hole in my coate, who catcheth ſo at a <note n="x" place="margin">Et fumus et fimus.</note> vapour, which is long ſince flowne out of his reach.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:4324:23"/>
               <head>§ 12.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He next flaw which he finds is <note n="a" place="margin">Pag. 135.</note> an imperfect Allegation of the ſame Father, without any direction where hee might finde it. In which he hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelfe a very kinde Aduerſarie, by quoting the place, and adding the words which were wanting. I will not requite him with the Prouerbe, that <hi>profered ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice merits ſmall thankes:</hi> but in lieu of his labour, I will more fully aduertiſe him of my ſcope, which hee ſeemes wholie to miſtake. My purpoſe was from a ground out of Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> to proue that the booke of <hi>Machabees</hi> is not Canonicall. My Major is S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> as well knowne as the Beggar knoweth his diſh, <hi>In libris Canonicis, nuſquam nobis praeceptum, permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumué, &amp;c. In holy Canonicall Scripture there is no diuine precept or permiſsion to be found, that either to gayne immortalitie or to eſcape
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:4324:24"/>
any perill we may make away with our ſelues: But</hi> Razias <hi>mentioned in the</hi> Machabees, <hi>is commended for a fact of this kinde:</hi> Ergo, <hi>Theſe bookes are not Canonicall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Syllogiſme</hi> I had a deſire to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. <note n="b" place="margin">Artis eſt artem diſſimulare.</note> Hee is a ſimple Painter that is dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to write a Gooſe, or a VVoodcocke ouer-head, that people may know what feature hee hath drawne vnderneath. Neither doe <hi>Rhethoricians</hi> vſe to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh their propoſitions by name, leaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worke for the <hi>Logicall Analyſis,</hi> to ſet euery part in the proper place: VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being then loath to be tedious to the <hi>Reader</hi> with long Quotations, I held it beſt to abridge two Authorities in one, and did forbeare to note the places, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I was reſolued to deliuer the words by waight, and not by tale.</p>
               <p>The words by mee deliuered were theſe: <hi>In ſanctis Canonicis libris nuſquàm no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis diuinitùs, praeceptum, permiſſumue repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riri poteſt, vt vel ipſius adipiſcendae immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitatis,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:4324:24"/>
vel vllius Carendi, Cauendi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> mali cauſa nobis ipſis necem inferamus. At</hi> Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zias <hi>ſeipſum occidens laudatur.</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Pag. 135.</note> 
                  <hi>Theſe foure words</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are added to the Text, S.</hi> Auguſtine <hi>hath them not. Farre was it from S.</hi> Auguſtines <hi>grauitie, to ſay, that</hi> Razias <hi>was therefore praiſed in the</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabees; <hi>For hee ſaith the contrary in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe termes, in the very ſame place againſt</hi> Gaudentius.</p>
               <p>I will not be the man, that ſhall ſet S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> at oddes with S. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> I could gladly haue concealed it, if there be any ſuch contradiction. But ſeeing hee ſues me to iuſtifie my Aſſumption, That <hi>Razias</hi> is therefore commended in the <hi>Machabees,</hi> I muſt referre you to <note n="d" place="margin">Lyra <hi>in</hi> 2 <hi>Mach.</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Lyra,</hi> 2 <hi>Mach.</hi> 14. VVhere hauing deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered two caſes, wherein the Iewes held it not onely lawfull, but meritorious for a man to kill himſelfe: as firſt, <hi>Ne ſubditus fieret peccatoribus:</hi> Secondly, <hi>Ne in contemptum Dei Coeli, eius vita in ludi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brio
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:4324:25"/>
haberetur:</hi> Hee concludes, <hi>Et vt dicunt aliqui, hoc modo intelligendum eſt dictum</hi> Auguſtini, <hi>quod habetur hic in Gloſſa:</hi> and, as ſome thinke, S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> ſaying, which followeth here in the Gloſſe, is thus to be vnderſtood. O that I could meete with that ſaying of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> which I omitted to cite. Doth <hi>Lyra</hi> ſay, it followeth here in the Gloſſe? then will I preſume ſo farre vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon your patience, as to write it out. <note n="e" place="margin">Lyra in Mach. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Vnde &amp; Scriptura huius Libri, quae recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta est ab Eccleſia ad legendum pro informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione morum, non videtur hic</hi> Raziam <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guere, ſed potiùs</hi> 
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Marke Mr. <hi>Rab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>echeth.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>commendare, de ſui ipſius interfectione. Si autem praedicta non ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt ad eius excuſationem, poteſt dici quod fecit hoc per ſpiritualem inſtinctum Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Sancti: Whereupon the Scripture of this Booke, which is receiued by the Church to be read, for the information of manners, doth not ſeeme here to reproue</hi> Razias, <hi>but rather to commend him for killing of himſelfe, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:4324:25"/>Now whether S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> were of this minde or no, let it lye vpon <hi>Lyraes</hi> report, who here relateth, eyther the very wordes, or the receiued ſenſe. Yet doth not this Sophiſter ſticke to ſay, <hi>It was farre from his grauitie, hee read not that Booke with ſo little ſobrietie.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, it is not much materiall, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing my Major out of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> that <hi>in no Canonicall Booke there is eyther Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept or Permiſsion for a man to kill him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi> it is ſufficient for mee, to proue from the aſſent, euen of the <hi>Rabbins,</hi> (albeit that Father had not iumped in this point, as hee ſeemes to doe,) that <hi>Razias</hi> is here commended: and ſo may conclude, <hi>That they are not Canonicall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How would this dizzie brainde <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malite</hi> haue inſulted, had I noted S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine, de Ciuitate Dei,</hi> in the Margent, for the whole, which error a man might eaſily haue committed vpon <hi>Lyraes</hi> warrant, that my Clauſe and Minor
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:4324:26"/>
Propoſition, <hi>that</hi> Razias <hi>is therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended,</hi> was not onely held by the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the <hi>Rabbins,</hi> but euen of Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> himſelfe: VVherefore as hee hath found Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> for the firſt part, let him put <hi>Lyra</hi> to the laſt, and then I will paſſe my word, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion ſhall be free from his ſuppoſed colluſion.</p>
               <p>Did I doubt of the agilitie of your apprehenſion, I could be more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixe in the explication thereof, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haue another Crow to pull with him, I will no further inlarge my Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie in this point.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:4324:26"/>
               <head>§ 13.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He laſt <note n="g" place="margin">Pag. 318.</note> occaſion which he pretends hath giuen him iuſt cauſe to carpe is, for that I ſaid <note n="h" place="margin">To Mr. <hi>T.H.</hi> Pag. 92.</note> 
                  <hi>our Engliſh nation was not conuerted vnto Chriſt by that proud and inſolent</hi> Auguſtine, <hi>their great</hi> Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries <hi>delegate: affirming that he taught vs no more, then wee knew before, ſetting ſome friuilous Ceremonies aſide.</hi> VVherevpon hee enforceth, <hi>that J neuer read that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-worke of the three Conuerſions of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> wherein the teſtimonie of <hi>Guildas,</hi> by mee cited, is largely handled and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared. Should I graunt all, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee what inconuenience will enſue. Is there no better imployment of my time, then the pervſall of that <hi>Arch-fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitiues</hi> lines? Or hath none beſides of their faction beaten this buſh, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped on the ſame ſtring? Or am I in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience bound to put the ſeale of my aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:4324:27"/>
to whatſoeuer F. <hi>Parſons</hi> did write? I confeſſe hee acknowledgeth that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was here, hee mentioneth alſo (perhaps vpon greater probabilitie) the comming of Saint <hi>Paul, Simon Zelotes, Ariſtobulus,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathaea.</hi> VVhere doe I ſay, that <hi>they weary the World, and bob their credulous Ladies, as if they neuer had heard of</hi> Gildas <hi>his Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie?</hi> I neuer named their Author, nor queſtioned that matter. Howſoeuer it pleaſe him to ioyne the pieces of two ſentences together, which are almoſt a whole Page diſtant; and to fetch his Marginall Note 92. Pages off.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gildas</hi> his teſtimonie (ſaid I) hath beene vrged that the <hi>Britaines</hi> receiued the Chriſtian Faith from the beginning, and after many ſuch like Inſtances, I conclude that theſe particulars haue beene againe and againe renewed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any verified contradiction; ſo farre was I from denying that their Author
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:4324:27"/>
mentioneth not theſe, whom I well know hee hath particularly cited. That which I wondred at, was this, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the former inſtances by them not denied, they ſhould ſtand ſo much vpon the Conuerſion of <hi>England,</hi> by Saint <hi>Gregories</hi> meanes; at which I onely aymed, as if that originall and primitiue Conuerſion, had beene a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which they neuer heard of before. VVhen they haue made the beſt they can of it, it will proue at the moſt to be but a new ſupply, and a further propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Goſpell formerly preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among the Inhabitants of this Land. For, if <hi>Britaine</hi> were many hundred yeeres before that time conuerted (as themſelues confeſſe,) then did not <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> lay the corner-ſtone himſelfe, but built vpon the Foundation of other men.</p>
               <p>So that the particulars were not by mee ſpecified, as if they denyed them,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:4324:28"/>
but to proue from their owne acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement, that they had therefore lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reaſon ſo to magnifie the enterance of that Delegate, with the glorious ſtile of the Conuerſion of this Engliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>§ 14.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow, whereas hee further replieth, that the people of this Country (the <hi>Britaines</hi> being expelled) were then Heathen: I demaund, whether hee found not in <hi>Britaine,</hi> at his Arriuall, amongſt the Engliſh <hi>Saxons,</hi> ſeauen Biſhops, and an Arch-biſhop, vvho were not onely Profeſſors, but alſo Preachers of the Chriſtian Faith? VVere there not at that in the Monaſterie of <hi>Bangor</hi> two thouſand Monkes? VVas not <note n="i" place="margin">Bed. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 25</note> Q. <hi>Aldiberga</hi> a good Chriſtian be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee came into <hi>Kent?</hi> or had the Biſhop her Chaplaine no Faith at all?
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:4324:28"/>
VVill hee not beleeue <hi>Bede,</hi> 
                  <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 17.</note> who wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that before <hi>Auguſtines</hi> comming, the <hi>Britaines</hi> were infected with <hi>Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme</hi> and <hi>Pelagianiſme?</hi> Perhaps this Cure deſerued the name of a Conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: yea, but <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was not the Phyſitian. The French-men (ſaith <hi>Bede</hi>) at the requeſt of the <hi>Britaines,</hi> met in a Synode, and ſent <hi>Germanus</hi> and <hi>Lupus,</hi> by whom the Heretiques were confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the auncient Faith reuiued, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Monke ſet foote vpon Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ground. But becauſe hee is ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident in the three Conuerſions, as if that Mallet were able to ſtrike all dead, let him learne from his owne Author, that which I beleeue hee will be ſcarſe willing to heare, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Part.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>n.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>That from the time of K.</hi> Lucius, <hi>vntill the comming of</hi> Auguſtine, <hi>which was foure hundred yeere and more, they did not alter their Faith, but it remained among them when hee entered.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:4324:29"/>VVhat is now become of this good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Conuerſion? Dares hee let his wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be examined any further? <hi>That Faith</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>which</hi> Auguſtine <hi>brought, and that which the</hi> Britaines <hi>had before, muſt needes bee one and the ſelfe-ſame in all materiall and ſubſtantiall Poynts.</hi> VVee ſhall not neede to vrge him with further Interrogatories, the Iewrie ſees hee failes in this Iſſue, and therefore their verdict will be, that <hi>It was onely a ſuperficiall, and no ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Conuerſion.</hi> Hath hee not now brought his Hoggs to a faire Market? Hath hee read the Booke of the three Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſions? The caſe is ſo cleare now, that his <note n="m" place="margin">Mulier nihil ſcit, niſi quod ipſa cupit.</note> Ladies ſhall be able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe it were a Conuerſion, I hope they preſume ſo farre vpon <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtines</hi> honeſtie, that hee would not broach any other Faith, then that which his Maſter, by whom hee was ſent,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:4324:29"/>
had giuen him in charge. If ſo, what will become of the Popes Supremacie, Images, Merits of workes, and the like traſh; which that <note n="n" place="margin">Catholike ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale for Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants. Way to the Chur. Sect. 49.</note> 
                  <hi>Gregorie</hi> was ſo farre from countenancing by his authoritie, that hee diſclaimed by his Penne? So that if he were a Founder, yet was it not of that Faith, which the B. of <hi>Romes</hi> Proctors doe now ſo ſtifly maintaine: and conſequently this imaginarie Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition will bruiſe their owne Pates. But how ſhall I then ſcape his hands for wronging <hi>Auguſtine?</hi> Hee cannot endure to heare him tearmed a proud and inſolent Delegate: indeede, vvere my Malice the Mynter of this contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melious reproach, I confeſſe hee had no reaſon to ſtand with his finger in his mouth; but hee might haue done well before hee had growne into ſuch a choler, to haue taken Counſell of the <hi>Britaine</hi> BB. <note n="o" place="margin">L. 2. C. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Bede</hi> would haue infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him how Lordly hee ſate in his
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:4324:30"/>
Chaire, like a little Pope, <note n="p" place="margin">Vultus animi index.</note> neither ariſing nor bowing to the BB. when they came into the Synode, more like a Lord, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing dominion of their Faith, then a Conuerter, beſeeching them in the Name of the Lord <hi>Ieſus.</hi> Thoſe BB. were not ſo ſimple, but they could <note n="q" place="margin">Ex vngue Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> diſcouer his Pride, and therefore ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured to ouer-thwart him in whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer hee propoſed. VVell did his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter perceiue his ambitious ſpirit, when hee gaue him this cooling Card touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the BB. of <hi>France;</hi> 
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Greg. <hi>reſp. ad inter.</hi> Aug. Bed. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 27.</note> 
                  <hi>In Galliarum Epiſcopos, nullam tibi authoritatem tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buimus: Wee giue you no authoritie ouer them.</hi> All this notwithſtanding, I muſt haue my lips ſealed, not daring to ſay, that <hi>Hee was a proud inſolent Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate.</hi> I ſee no reaſon why <hi>vitium</hi> and <hi>conuitium</hi> ſhould be parted: ſeeing hee deſerued it, hee is beſt vvorthy to haue it.</p>
               <p>VVere I now in his caſe, I ſhould be
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:4324:30"/>
in a pittifull feare leaſt the Noble <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> whom hee hath ſo groſſely delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſhould like ſo many <hi>Hecubaes,</hi> ſeeke ſome violent reuenge: what ſtarting hole can there be poſſibly found, to hide theſe his writing falſifications from their curious eyes? when they ſhall perceiue how he coniures my ſentences together, to raiſe his owne ſence, hee may well thinke their Contributions will be ſoone ſhortned, and Exhibitions reuoked: farre is it from their generous diſpoſitions to giue incouragement to any ſuch audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Vaſſall, in the cauſleſſe traducing of a Knight, to whom their Honors is no leſſe deare then his owne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:4324:31"/>
               <head>§ 15.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F hee haue any Plea for himſelfe, it will be this; that <note n="s" place="margin">Pag. 133. 135 22. 218. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>hee doth not charge the Knight with theſe ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and impudent cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions: No, hee thinkes not ſo diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably of men of my calling; hee aymes onely at the Miniſter that ſuggeſted vnto mee theſe corrupted pieces of Saint</hi> Auguſtine. <hi>His purpoſe was onely to gall thoſe Pedan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Trencher-Schoole-Maſters, and humo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing Diſcourſers, that caſt ſuch Flies and follies vpon my Trenchers: If hee haue taxed mee with ignorance, that is pardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in a Knight: but as for notorious falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoodes, hee is ſo charitably perſwaded of mee, that hee knowes ſome Trencher-Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, or Mercenarie Lecturer, (yea, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> Craſhawe <hi>himſelfe, who is great in my Booke,) hath caſt them on my Trencher, to put into my Booke: and that theſe Miniſters
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:4324:31"/>
haue made mee print ſuch ſtuffe, eyther falſe, or impertinent, with the loſſe of my Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, which had I ſeene their Bookes I would neuer haue done againſt my Conſcience and knowledge.</hi> Adding further, <hi>that what J haue written, it hath beene by their ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, as hauing my ſelfe not read, nor knowne ſo much as the ſubiect and Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the three Conuerſions of</hi> England, <hi>which I ſeeme to ſpeake againſt: and that theſe are the men that made mee flye hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winck'd to catch Flyes.</hi> In fine, <hi>as for any thing that hee hath written, it was to no other end, but that I might no longer truſt my Trencher-Schoole-Maſters, but ſet ſuch a frowne vpon them, that they might va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh out of my ſight for euer; not ſuffering my ſelfe to be thus troubled, and my Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit blowne vp, but rather to lay the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Pamphlet vpon the true Father, onely chalenging to my ſelfe the Stile and Phraſe which may well beſeeme a Knight, and is too rich and golden to clothe the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:4324:32"/>
foule Brat of a Miniſters Braine.</hi> Thus doth hee pleade without his Fee, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Salue worſe then the <note n="(t)" place="margin">Cauda &amp; capite mendacium gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiter ferit.</note> Sore: firſt, treading on my Toe, and then cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mee mercy: but the beſt is, I am not troubled with Cornes, or if I were, I would ſoone cut them out. VVhat hee ſtriues to perſwade the world with my diſabilitie, I am not ſo <note n="(u)" place="margin">Conuitia homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num turpium laudes puta.</note> popular much to heed: neyther can his <note n="(x)" place="margin">Cani latranti praeda facilè, ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur.</note> ſnarling ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes abate one graine of my eſteeme. My eyes are not yet, I thanke God, ſo dim, but that I am able to reade; nor my apprehenſion ſo dull, but that I can vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, not onely the Argument, but euen the moſt artificiall conueyance of the beſt of their VVorkes.</p>
               <p>Vpon my life hee hath beene an old notorious Truant: Had he made <note n="(y)" place="margin">Sic vos non vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis.</note> his owne Exerciſes vvhen hee vvent to Schoole, hee would neuer haue beene ſo ſuſpicious of my Penne. Is it not ſtrange ſuch a Dottrell, ſhould ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:4324:32"/>
of his owne wit, as if hee were able to wooe me to diuide mine owne childe? I aſſure mee, that all that know me, will vndertake I was not from home when it was begotten. How eaſily would I haue beleeued him vpon his word, that there was no hand in the building of his <note n="(z)" place="margin">Nec oleum, nec operam ſapit.</note> Pinnace, but his owne; yet will not hee take my <note n="(a)" place="margin">Ego credidi an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillae tuae, tu non credis mihi ipſi?</note> hand for the naturalizing of my owne Lines, which as I had ſtrength to beget, ſo doubt I not to finde ſtocke to maintaine. VVere I ſo happy to ſee him at my <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Table, (which runs much in his minde) I preſume I ſhould ſo ſet his tongue a-worke, that he ſhould doe mee little harme with his teeth. Hee ſhould perhaps then finde, that I am yet able to cite more then a piece of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> without a Prompter; and to caſt ſuch a Bone vpon his Trencher, that with all the Dogges teeth he hath, hee ſhould hardly picke. I haue ſeene in my time, as tall a <hi>Logician</hi> as hee,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:4324:33"/>
glad to ſcratch the beſt powle hee had for an anſwere. As I was euer different from their humour who loue to eate their morſels <note n="(c)" place="margin">Vbi ſolitudo ibi ſolicitudo.</note> alone, ſo hath it euer beene my deſire to conuerſe with men of the <note n="(d)" place="margin">Plenum Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum eſt vir bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, viro bono.</note> beſt parts, that ſo I might by their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings better my ſelfe. And if at any time I met with a hard knot, hee was the beſt welcome to mee, that could helpe mee ſooneſt to vnlooſe it. Neuer did I truſt ſo much to mine owne Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, but that I was well content to haue it eyther confirmed, or rectified by better Iudgements. If this be a fault, I wiſh from my heart it were the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt my aduerſaries knew by me, or I by my ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:4324:33"/>
               <head>§ 16.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doe not reade in <hi>Gellius</hi> that there was any fault found in <hi>Gracchus,</hi> albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it hee came not at any time to make an Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the people without his Minſtrell, who by the ſound of his <note n="(e)" place="margin">Fiſtula Concio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natoris.</note> Pipe, did ſet him a right and iuſt Keye for the eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or depreſſing of his voyce. VVhen I was an <hi>Eaton</hi>-Scholar, I learned out of <hi>Lucians</hi> Dialogues, that <hi>Iupiter</hi> was faine to ſend for <hi>Vulcan</hi> and his hatchet, before <hi>Pallas</hi> could come into the world: So that I cannot well diſcerne what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hee hath to debarre mee of that conference at my Boord, which their owne Doctors haue in their Libraries. If happily I did moue a Queſtion, how S. <hi>Augustine</hi> was in ſuch a place to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, it did argue my <note n="(f)" place="margin">Plus vident ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li quam oculus.</note> care in ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the depth of the Riuer, before I
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:4324:34"/>
launched my Barke into the Streame. I was euer of <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> minde in this, that my writings ſhould not onely ſmell of the <note n="(g)" place="margin">Lucernam olet.</note> Lampe, but if it were poſſible, be engrauen alſo in <note n="(h)" place="margin">Atilan ok dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</note> Marble. But that I euer ſuffered my Penne to be guided, or my courſe ouer-ruled by any other Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot then my owne <hi>Genius,</hi> were hee not a meere ſtranger to my proceedings, hee would neuer be ſo ſhameleſſe as to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerre. Though it be my error, yet I muſt needes ſay, I could neuer endure to let my Clarke paſſe any Letter, but from my owne mouth: And ſhould the greateſt Architect in the Land, giue mee a plot for a building, I am verily perſwaded, I ſhould in the end take a cleane contrary courſe. VVhen I can hardly pleaſe my ſelfe, it will be a matter of more difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for others to giue me content. Euery man (as I take it) hath his proper <note n="(i)" place="margin">Quot capita, tot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> veine: for my particular I dare ſay, it is vnpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for the pallat of my fancie, to be
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:4324:34"/>
fitted by any other Cooke then my ſelfe. Should I haue eyther an Adjutor, or Superviſor, in any worke I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, I thinke it would proue little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the confuſion of <hi>Babell:</hi> VVee ſhould ſooner fall together by the eares, then bring the Treatiſe to an end.</p>
               <p>The ſhort is, I am <hi>Homo perpaucorum hominum,</hi> though ſeeming a VVidower, yet contracted to M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi>. <hi>Folly:</hi> I can glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heare what others will ſay, yet when it comes to the point, I loue to doe what <note n="(k)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> likes my ſelfe beſt. VVherefore hee hath taken wrong courſe, to wound M. <hi>Craſhawe</hi> (a man with whom I neuer had the leaſt domeſtique conuerſe,) through my ſides.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:4324:35"/>
               <head>§ 17.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND as for Houſe-<hi>Pedantes, Trencher-Schoole-Maſters,</hi> and <hi>Mercenary-Lecturers,</hi> he that reades my bitter (yet iuſt)<note n="l" place="margin">To Mr. <hi>T. H.</hi> Pag. 24.</note> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uectiue againſt them, will thinke they haue as little reaſon to aſſiſt mee, as I to truſt them. VVherefore I cannot gueſſe, why hee ſhould caſt this foggy miſt of miſpriſion before the eyes of the world: (euer and anone comming in vvith <hi>A Miniſter of his owne making,</hi>) vnleſſe it were couertly to vpbraid mee, for med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in Theologicall affaires, as better beſeeming a Miniſter then a Knight. Herein though I could inſtance in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of greater place, euen in former ages, who by publiſhing their labours in the like ſubiect, were ſo farre from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, that they were much more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by men of the Church: yet had I rather repaire for defence to my owne
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:4324:35"/>
Studies, which (ſetting ſome fantaſticall yeeres aſide) hath for the moſt part beene ſpent in diuine Authors. My <note n="(m)" place="margin">Diteſcit cui Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus dulceſcit.</note> Patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie (God be thanked) being competent, I endeuoured rather the ſearch of my content, then my profit. And what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter contentation can there be, then the contemplation of <note n="(n)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> heauenly things? If he ſay, I might haue kept my Candle vnder my owne Buſhell, I muſt anſwere that his opinion is no Oracle: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides ſome other priuate motiues, I held it not inexpedient, euen in this regard, that the truth might be defended by perſons whoſe pennes could not be corrupted with ambitious hope of <note n="(o)" place="margin">Becauſe (ſaith he) they haue no other meanes to liue. Pag. 31.</note> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall promotions.</p>
               <p>Further, the report of the VVriter might happily induce the <hi>Ladies</hi> to vouchſafe the reading thereof, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as their Prieſts debars them the ſight of our Miniſters Bookes. I was loath ſuch rare creatures ſhould be ouer gudgeoned
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:4324:36"/>
by ſo foule <hi>Popinians,</hi> by whom, when their treaſure is once waſted, and their younger yeeres ſpent, they ſhall be no more eſteemed, then ſo many Mothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaten Gloſſes: which (albeit they haue formerly ſtood them in ſtead) they are not now aſhamed to diſclaime.</p>
               <p>Other incitements I had then to write, which he hath neyther authoritie to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort, nor I reaſon to declare. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I then paſſed my word, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere any <note n="(p)" place="margin">To M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>T. H.</hi> Pag. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Romefied Renegado,</hi> though I haue ſmall reaſon to defile my fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers with ſuch a <hi>Pezantique Fugitiue,</hi> who is aſhamed of his <note n="q" place="margin">Les eſcrits iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieux doiuent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre meſpriſes quand les au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teurs ſont in cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus. <hi>P. Mat.</hi>
                  </note> Fathers name: yet leaſt my ſilence might preiudice ſo warrantable a cauſe, I haue clapt my hand vpon this Gnat, which keepeth ſuch an humming about my eares. This I was not ignorant of before I tooke my penne in hand for this combat, that I ſhould gaine no more by coping with a nameleſſe Foe, then the Lord
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:4324:36"/>
Chiefe Iuſtice <note n="(r)" place="margin">Not long after the Statute made for bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of rogues in the eare.</note> 
                  <hi>Cataline</hi> got, when his Studie was robbed, by the paper which was there left, with this Inſcription:
<q>
                     <l>If any aske who hath beene here,</l>
                     <l>Say it was<note n="(s)" place="margin">
                           <hi>I. R.</hi> Nomen &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>en.</note> Iack Rogue late burnt in the eare.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>§. 18.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Perſon not long ſince of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent place, eſteemed not leaſt Politicall, after he had beene often (as himſelfe ſaith) vexed with their <note n="(t)" place="margin">Quò triſtis E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynnis, quò fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitus vocat. <hi>Virg. 2. Aeneid.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Erynnicall</hi> Libels, (which are ordinarily addreſſed to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of higheſt rancke) at laſt vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed a briefe <note n="(u)" place="margin">An Anſwere to certaine ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Papers, printed 1606.</note> Apologeticall anſwere; but with this proteſtation, that hee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer intended further Reply. VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as while he liued, Nature caſt this lot vpon me, to be one of the neareſt of his bloud; ſo though hee be dead, I will iumpe with his diſcretion in this, that if eyther this <hi>Cat-ſputtrer,</hi> or any other <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garen</hi> ſhall hereafter inter-lace my name
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:4324:37"/>
in their <hi>Spiders Web,</hi> 
                  <note n="(x)" place="margin">Periti bellatoris eſt, non minus ſcire fugiendi ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem quam pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandi.</note> 
                  <hi>aut Dormitabo, aut Ridebo.</hi> VVere not the darkneſſe of my <note n="(y)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> VVindowes a ſufficient <hi>Superſedeas,</hi> yet ſhall I by this meanes turne their Follies and friuolous Contumelies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Trophies of my victorious Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience. VVhereas, <note n="(z)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 26.4.</note> 
                  <hi>By anſwering a foole according to his fooliſhneſſe, J ſhould alſo be held like vnto him.</hi> It is more then enough, that I haue thus farre yeelded to <note n="(a)" place="margin">Pag. 52.</note> bray him in this Morter, with the Peſtle of my Penne; if the iuyce be vnpleaſing, you muſt attribute it to the venome of his cankered Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: better things I could not extract from ſuch an Aſpe.</p>
               <p>If you ſeriouſly obſerue his lame and goutie Arguments, his dangerous intention, and ſlender proſecution, you ſhall finde iuſt ground to ſay of his Treatiſe, as <note n="(b)" place="margin">Populi Romani legationem, nec pedes, habere, nec caput, nec cor.</note> 
                  <hi>Cato</hi> merrily ſpake of the three Ambaſſadours, who being named for <hi>Bithinia,</hi> excuſed themſelues; one by
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:4324:37"/>
a cut in his head, another with a paine in his feete, and the third with a gry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in his heart: neither whole head, good feete, nor ſound heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>§ 19.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N his Preface Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, hee brags, that hee hath ſent out his Booke, as a Pinnace, to fetch you into the Arke of the Catholike Church: But I feare by that time M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Craſhawe</hi> hath ſearched his bottome, it will proue no better then a leaking Friggot. His Sailes are too great for a Veſſell of ſo ſmall burthen, and conſequently moſt like to indanger the Paſſengers ſafetie. If all thoſe Bookes, which hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines are not ſuffered to paſſe our <note n="(c)" place="margin">Pag. 89.</note> 
                  <hi>Ports</hi> (except almoſt inuiſible) be like this <note n="(d)" place="margin">Pag. 8</note> 
                  <hi>Dung-hill</hi> of his, let it euer be regiſtred in the Booke of fame, amongſt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:4324:38"/>
the due Commendations of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, ſuperlatiuely learned, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <note n="(e)" place="margin">Lo. Warden of the Cincque Ports.</note> Councellor, to whoſe care this important charge is committed; that hee hath herein teſtified his loue to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, fidelitie to his Prince, and loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie to the State: As his wiſedome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues to be admired, and his lenitie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded, ſo doth his ſinceritie herein merit high renowne in the Gates of our <hi>Sion.</hi> For ſhould the infectious Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of theſe peſtilent incrochers be paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable in our Coaſt, the contagion would be ſuch, that true Pietie could not long holde vp the head, nor due Allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance be able to ſtand vpon her right feete. The giddineſſe which <note n="(f)" place="margin">Superſtitio ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium prabuit, &amp; ortum impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati.</note> 
                  <hi>Superſtition</hi> would breede, and the Diſobedience which <hi>Papall Authoritie</hi> would raiſe in the mindes of the vnlearned, vvhoſe Capacities are not able to reach the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture perill of Innouation, would be ſo dangerous to a Chriſtian, and vvell
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:4324:38"/>
gouerned State, that it would aske the whole imployment of the moſt experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced <hi>Senators,</hi> to roote out the weedes which thoſe enuious impes had ſowne. All which will be preuented if at their firſt Arriuall they be caſt <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not neede any further to wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry my ſelfe, or tyre you, with the repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of thoſe inuectiues which this <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebrio</hi> hath ſharpened vpon the VVhet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of his malice, to wound my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation. This ſhall I hope ſuffice, that I haue as neare as I could, ſolidly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered things of waight, dealing in points of leſſer import, as I thought their qualitie did require.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:4324:39"/>
               <head>§ 20.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE due regard which I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer had of your iudgements (hauing my ſelfe beene ſometimes an vnworthy member of the ſame <note n="(h)" place="margin">Middle Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> Societie) hath made mee deſirous not onely to ſend my Defence after his accuſations, but alſo to ſecond it with a further mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of my Loue.</p>
               <p>May it then pleaſe you to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that howſoeuer hee ſeeke to inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate himſelfe by his charitable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences into the boſome of your fauors, yet hath hee not left his <note n="(i)" place="margin">Loquitur men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacia verſipellis. <hi>Pag. 12.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Scorpions</hi> ſting at home: For notwithſtanding hee fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers his Dedication vpon the <note n="(k)" place="margin">Pag. 22.</note> carefull reſpect of your Saluation and Honour, yet doth hee make no other reckoning of you, then of ſo many <note n="(l)" place="margin">Pag. 81.</note> 
                  <hi>Parlamentari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> whoſe Religion is ſteared by the Helme of the State, as if the Bookes of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:4324:39"/>
Statutes vvere the ſole foundations of your Faith. Neyther doth hee ſticke to ſay that you make your <note n="(m)" place="margin">Pag. 59.</note> 
                  <hi>Temples and Courts the places where ſilly Flies and fooles are caught, by your example as with a ſtale drawing others into the Snare.</hi> If this be the honor he beſtowes vpon his friends, I will neuer be importunate with him to grace mee. Doe you remember what <hi>Gracchus</hi> ſaid to a fellow that ſpake in diſgrace of the vertuous Matron, his Mother <hi>Cornelia?</hi> 
                  <note n="(n)" place="margin">Eraſ. Apoth.</note> 
                  <hi>Tune, inquit,</hi> Corneli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am <hi>vituperare audes, que</hi> Tyberium <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perit? Dare thou</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>traduce her, who brought ſo famous a Sonne as</hi> Tibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius? The like anſwere might I retort in the teeth of this <hi>Therſites.</hi> Is he not paſt all hope of future ingenuitie, that faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his taunt vpon the venerable Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſo many honourable Sonnes, ſaying, <note n="(o)" place="margin">Pag. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>That ſhee is more full of Cobwebs then any other place?</hi> Did <hi>Scipio Naſcica</hi> aske one which had a tough and rough
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:4324:40"/>
hand, <note n="(p)" place="margin">Rogauit homine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, num manibus ambularet.</note> 
                  <hi>whether hee vſed to goe vpon his hands?</hi> then, ſhould he haue ſeene the brazen fore-head of this ſawcie Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert, hee might iuſtly haue demaunded whether hee hath not cuſtomarily crept vpon his face. It is well knowne to the Chriſtian world, that theſe your famous Courts haue brought forth, euen in theſe latter yeeres, as many <note n="(q)" place="margin">Tanquam eu E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Treiane.</note> ſage Councellors of State, religious Iudges, gallant Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, learned Pleaders, and worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, as the Sunne euer ſaw. In which number I may both for his merit, and my reſpect, name that truely Noble Peere the Lo. <hi>Elmſmere,</hi> in whom it is hard to ſay, whether wiſedome in the deciſion, or integritie in the impartiall execution of Iuſtice haue the prioritie. VVell doe I aſſure my ſelfe, hee would neyther ſpare his authoritie, nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare his beſt meanes to keepe <hi>Spiders</hi> from breeding, and <hi>Cobwebs</hi> from grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in thoſe Courts, wherein himſelfe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:4324:40"/>
hath ſpent much time, and gained ſo great renowne. So that the <hi>Fan</hi> of truth which he offereth to cleanſe your Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, may better be reſerued by him, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to keepe off the Mothes from the olde Gloſſes, or the Flyes from the Prieſts <note n="(r)" place="margin">Poſt ſumptos Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lices oſcula muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca dabit.</note> lips: Herein you may doe the Pope yeoman ſeruice indeede.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>§ 21.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Greater Commendations there cannot be vnto you that are Students, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the Lawes of the Realme, then to manifeſt the ſincere affection you beare to true Religion, by your liberall Contributions to ſuch as may inſtruct you in the Lawes of God. The quarrell hee pickes with you about this, will more deepely imprint the Charecters of your praiſe. Should you paſſe the preſentation to him, who can tell what Lecturer hee would no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate?
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:4324:41"/>
No doubt hee would come in with, <hi>Ego Iſhmael Rabſbacheh,</hi> 
                  <note n="(s)" place="margin">Pag. 149.</note> 
                  <hi>Domino Deo noſtro Papa à ſcandalis praeſento vobis, dilectum commilitonem meum</hi> 
                  <note n="(t)" place="margin">I. R.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſcharioth de Rubigine, quemſcio Homiliſtam eſſe egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium, Bibulum celeberrimum, Cantorem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> non vulgarem, id<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vobis meâ, fidê praeſto, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> contubernio.</hi> Yea marry, here is a fine Demilance for the nonce: here is one that will be the formoſt attendant vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my Lo. of the Reuels; Hee will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer holde you a quarter after the glaſſe is runne. But can you gueſſe what Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triman hee is? For his life hee is not able to pronounce <note n="(u)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Shibboleth.</hi> VVhy then, you will none of him! O beware of a <hi>quare impedit.</hi> But the beſt is, you haue the Law in your hands. You haue a purſe priuiledge to be your owne Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. If the worſe come that can, you may diſmiſſe him to ſerue the Cure at <hi>Pemblico:</hi> and ſo perhaps you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine your old choiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:4324:41"/>Yea, but M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Craſhawe</hi> hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuch an error, as deſerueth depriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>ipſo facto:</hi> VVot you what? in his <hi>Ieſuites Goſpell</hi> hee makes <note n="(x)" place="margin">Pag. 76.</note> 
                  <hi>Dux Cleri</hi> to be the Popes chiefeſt title: which (if wee may beleeue our Informer) was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer giuen him by any Catholike, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther belongs to the Lo. of <hi>Canterburie.</hi> I will not be ſo curious to ſtand vpon the number of 666. thence collected; but, ſet that aſide, I dare ſay; <hi>Crux Cleri</hi> had beene the better word for the Pope: and yet to meete with him at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, I hold <hi>Dux Cleri</hi> to be but a part of my <hi>Lo. Graces</hi> Title, who by the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his affable diſpoſition, bounty in Hoſpitalitie, painfulneſſe in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and dexteritie in the diſpach of all occurrences, hath well deſerued the Stile of <hi>Lux Cleri,</hi> as being ſuch a light <hi>in Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro &amp; Foro,</hi> that if a man ſhould ſearch (like <hi>Diogenes</hi>) amongſt all the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, hee ſhould miſſe of his match. So
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:4324:42"/>
that mee thinkes the matter neede not be held ſo haynous, if hee haue taken that part which my Lord might beſt ſpare, to pay the Pope more then his due. I ſee there is then no great reaſon of complaint: what other Cauils they haue againſt him, I am neyther ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the proceedings, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted in the cauſe, to debate.</p>
               <p>Touching my ſelfe, (all due reſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion remembred) I conclude with him, whoſe queſtionable authoritie hath bred theſe broyles: <note n="(y)" place="margin">Mach. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi> v. <hi>39.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>If I haue done well, and as the matter required, it is the thing that I deſired: but if I haue written <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſlenderly and barely, it is that</hi> (which on the ſodaine) <hi>I could.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, you muſt accept it, as dedicated to your ſeruice.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From</hi> Iames <hi>Parke,</hi>
                     <date>Iune 21. 1613.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Edward Hoby.</signed>
               </closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:4324:42"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
